<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <channel>

        <title>Dennis Tenen - News and Updates</title>
        <description>  </description>
        <link>http://localhost:4000</link> 

        
        

            <item>

                <title> Hapax legomena </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;As as some friends know, I’ve been obssessed with &lt;em&gt;hapax legomena&lt;/em&gt; for some time, and I secretly plot an unwieldy pet project based on them. As anyone familiar with Middle Hebrew lexicography knowns, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus:text:1999.04.0057:entry=a%28/pac&quot;&gt;ἅπαξ λεγόμενον&lt;/a&gt; refers to utterances said only once, although more precisely it refers to words or expressions that register a single occurrence in a language corpus, and thus their meaning is difficult to establish with all certainty. In the context of Biblical textual scholarship, where the concept originated, it refers either to the whole set of 1300 words that occur only once in Biblical Hebrew, or to the more restricted set of about 400 words whose meaning cannot be derived from known roots.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If one considers the definition of the former set, hapax are not that uncommon: they account, for instance, for 44% of &lt;em&gt;Moby Dick&lt;/em&gt;, and their distribution is in fact predicted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zipf%27s_law&quot;&gt;Zipf’s law&lt;/a&gt;, which as I understand it simply states that there’s a roughly inversely proportional relation ruling the frequency of words, so any given word is half as likely to occur than the previous more frequent word. It’s easy to imagine the quickly plummeting statistical curve that ensues from such law. Under the second definition, as I understand it, hapax phenomena are much more contingent, distributed unequally across a corpus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what caught my attention today, while reading an &lt;a href=&quot;http://autocento.acdw.net&quot;&gt;intriguing piece of hypertextual literature&lt;/a&gt;, was the idea that, of course, different exegetical traditions built around specific linguistic corpora (say, Melville scholars or Medieval Rabbis) approach the problem of interpretation or translation of hapax legomena differently. As the mysterious Case Duckworth writes, while it’s conceivable that Mayan scholars leave a blank in their reading of an inscription, &lt;a href=&quot;http://autocento.acdw.net/about.html&quot;&gt;Biblical scholars cannot but translate hapax legomena&lt;/a&gt;. Critical interpretation might tolerate bracketed terms, but the superior call of theological consistency and public morality cannot plausibly presume tremor of intent on the part of the Godhead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A much more interesting —but, alas, impenetrable to me— discussion on Rabbinic scholar’s understanding of hapax legomena &lt;a href=&quot;https://books.google.com/books?id=KeY8DwAAQBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA308&amp;amp;dq=hapax+legomenon&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwj9lbSn4v3ZAhWpslQKHQlrAQcQ6AEIQzAF#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=hapax%20legomenon&amp;amp;f=false&quot;&gt;can be read here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>

                <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/think.stack/legomenon</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/think.stack/legomenon</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> Shorthand, he wrote </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;In the December 1893 issue of &lt;em&gt;The Shorthand Review&lt;/em&gt;, a diligent reader reported his discovery, while examining the historic monuments of Westminster Abbey, of a monument ereceted in the memory of a “competent stenographer.” In the north cloister of the Abbey, the anonymous reader of the Review found a “quaint tablet”, bearing a funerary inscription dedicated to William Laurence, who died in December 28, 1621, at age 29 —a tender age even for a stenographer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;With diligence and trvst most exemplary&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Did William Laurence serve as Prebendary&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;And for his paines now past before not lost&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Gain’d this remembrance at his master’s costs.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;O read these lines again; you seldome find&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;A Servant faithfvl and a master kind.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Shorthand he wrote; his flowre in prime did fade,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;And hasty Dead Short-Hand of him hath made.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Well covld he nu’bers, and well mesur’d Land;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Thus doth he now that drov’ed whereon you stand,&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Wherein he lyes so geometricall;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Art maketh some, but thus will Nature all.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
  &lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s ignore, for a moment, that this is the oldest use of the word “shorthand” on record for a lost art that until then was known as tachygraphy, or the likelihood that the term arose out of the need to fit this somber joke in a verse at the expense of a young prebend beloved by his master. The image is striking, and I personally find it deeply saddening: Death as a dutiful secretary, abridging lifes so save paper.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>

                <pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2018 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/think.stack/shorthand</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/think.stack/shorthand</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> En la viña del texto </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;Estas palabras de Ivan Illich:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/@illich2002vi%C3%B1edo78.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;La página como viñedo.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>

                <pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/think.stack/Vi%C3%B1edodelTexto</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/think.stack/Vi%C3%B1edodelTexto</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> Bibliógrafos y recolectores de documentos </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;Por razones que valdría la pena explorar, en México han escollado como en pocos sitios los bibliofilos y bibliógrafos. “Algunos de estos maniacos—escribía Luis González y González—han llegado a ser glorias nacionales, epónimos de avenidas como don Francisco del Paso y Troncoso.” En esta entrada, me propongo recopilar las principales colecciones documentales publicadas de documentos relativos a la Nueva España. Empiezo con los repertorios publicados por la española Academia de la Historia a mediados del siglo XIX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/009647708&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Colección de documentos inéditos relativos al descubrimiento, conquista y organización de las posesiones españolas de América y Oceanía&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Madrid, 1864-1888, 42 vols.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/006128301&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Colección de documentos ineditos relativos al descubrimiento, conquista y organización de las antiguas posesiones españolas de Ultramar (Segunda serie)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Madrid, 1885-1932, 25 vols.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Francisco del Paso y Troncoso, &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000502833&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Papeles de la Nueva España&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, Madrid, 1905-1906, 7 vols. &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000502833&quot;&gt;Suplementos&lt;/a&gt;, 1945-1948, 3 vols.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Francisco del Paso y Troncoso, &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/010520238&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Epistolario de la Nueva España, 1505-1818&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, México, 1939-1942, 16 vols.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joaquín García Icazbalceta, &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/001445216&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Colección de documentos para la historia de México&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, México 1858, 1866, 2 vols.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joaquín García Icazbalceta, &lt;a href=&quot;https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/ls?field1=ocr;q1=Nueva%20colección%20de%20documentos%20para%20la%20historia%20de%20Mexico;a=srchls;lmt=ft&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nueva colección de documentos para la historia de México&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, México, 1886-1892, 5 vols.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Joaquín García Icazbalceta, &lt;a href=&quot;https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/000699116&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Códice Mendieta: documentos franciscanos, siglos XVI y XVII&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, México, 1982, 2 vols.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manuel Orozco y Berra, &lt;em&gt;Documentos para la historia de México&lt;/em&gt;, México, 1853-1857, 4 series, 15 vols.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</description>

                <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2017 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/Bibliographers</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Bibliographers</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> Bachofen, Hercules </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.artic.edu/aic/collections/citi/images/standard/WebLarge/WebImg_000047/29488_489351.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Hercules&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En una pasaje lacónico del &lt;em&gt;Mutterrecht&lt;/em&gt;, Bachofen afirma que la transgresión de Prometeo fue naturalizada “trece generaciones más tarde” por Hércules. Es evidente que Bachofen se refiere a uno de los eventos menos comentados que integran el XI Trabajo de Hércules. De camino a las Hespérides, tras librarse de Kyknos, hijo de Ares, y Antaeus, hijo de Poseidón, Hércules recala en el Cáucaso. Ahí, en un risco, yace Prometeo encadenado. Hércules da muerte al águila que, cada noche, devora el hígado del antiguo titán. En agradecimiento, Prometeo revela al héroe la ubicación del jardín de las Hespérides, que resguarda las manzanas de oro. De acuerdo al jurista suizo, este evento constituye el postergado desenlace de pugna de Prometeo y los dioses olímpicos. A Hércules, el vencedor de monstruos, le corresponde, sin saberlo, naturalizar el “ethos prometeico” más allá de todo reparo de los olímpicos. De ahí que a menudo se le atribuya la invención de las artes, notablemente la escritura y la astronomía, artes que permiten a los hombres acceder a las formas futuras y remediar así la incuria de Epimeteo, ese titán que vive absorto en la inmanencia. La celebridad de Hércules supondría así, siguiendo a Bachofen, el definitivo olvido de Epimeteo, que ya en el tardío Hesiodo se ha convertido en el tonto por antonomasia. Desde entonces, la inmanencia que regía el orden matriarcal es sacrificada en los altares del Telos, que rige el orden del patriarcado: el paso del reino de la material al reino de la forma. Para entonces, la &lt;em&gt;physis&lt;/em&gt; primigenia sólo puede ya ser pensada como lo monstruoso, lo que el héroe, ufano en su &lt;em&gt;phronesis&lt;/em&gt; y primera víctima de la razón instrumental, debe destruir. De esto y otros temas me gusta imaginar que discutieron Ivan Illich y Erich Fromm una tarde de 1970 en Cuernavaca.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>

                <pubDate>Mon, 06 Mar 2017 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/think.stack/Hercules_Bachofen</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/think.stack/Hercules_Bachofen</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> Didascalia from the Didascalicon </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;http://hipomenes.github.io/2015/11/24/motto/&quot;&gt;written before&lt;/a&gt; about the pleasures of knowledge according to a Roman academy and Kircher’s adoption of a Platonic motto on the beauty of knowing everything. Last night, a little before falling asleep, I stumbled upon Hugh of Saint Victor’s praise of &lt;em&gt;meditatio&lt;/em&gt;, a practice closely related to the &lt;em&gt;lectio divina&lt;/em&gt;. It is, without doubt, the most beautiful praise of intellectual work I’ve read, an activity that according to Hugh gives us, in Jerome Taylor’s elegant translation, a “foretaste of the sweetness of eternal quiet”. In &lt;em&gt;meditatio&lt;/em&gt;, the rumination characteristic of the &lt;em&gt;lectio divina&lt;/em&gt; is carried forth beyond the confines of the book and into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/med1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On Meditation 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/med2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;On Meditation 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>

                <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/think.stack/A-didascalia-from-the-Didascalicon</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/think.stack/A-didascalia-from-the-Didascalicon</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> Mediterranean </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;Judíos, musulmanes, cristianos en el (nuevo) Mediterráneo. Un crash-course con énfasis en Al Andalus:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Abulafia, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Great-Sea-Human-History-Mediterranean/dp/019931599X?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;*Version*=1&amp;amp;*entries*=0&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Great Sea: A Human History of the Mediterranean&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Peter N. Miller, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Peirescs-Mediterranean-World-Peter-Miller-ebook/dp/B00W98ZUNS/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1464764319&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=miller+peiresc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Peiresc’s Mediterranean&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Emilio González Ferrín, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.casadellibro.com/libro-historia-general-de-al-andalus/9788488586810/1101167&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historia general de Al Andalús&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;David Niremberg, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/N/bo18602093.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Neighboring Faiths, Christianity, Islam and Judaism in the Middle Ages and Today&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Steven M. Wasserstrom, &lt;a href=&quot;http://press.princeton.edu/titles/5729.html&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Between Muslim and Jew: The Problem of Symbiosis under Early Islam&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Al-Andalus: paradigma y continuidad&lt;/em&gt;, ed. por González Ferrín&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simon R. Doubleday, &lt;a href=&quot;http://simondoubleday.com/writings/wise-king-christian-prince-muslim-spain-birth-renaissance&quot;&gt;The Wise King: A Christian Prince, Muslim Spain, and the Birth of the Renaissance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ver también la nota &lt;a href=&quot;http://bactra.org/notebooks/world-history.html&quot;&gt;World History, Macrohistory&lt;/a&gt; de C. Bactra. Y, por qué no, la serie &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b06rwgdf&quot;&gt;Blood and Gold&lt;/a&gt; de la BBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Less a real history that an incendiary manifesto. Many of his theses are not seconded by other scholars or, rather, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.abc.es/historia/abci-alejandro-garcia-sanjuan-negar-musulmanes-conquistaron-peninsula-iberica-disparate-201512070530_noticia.html&quot;&gt;are rebuked with the strongest terms&lt;/a&gt;. The most notable of these is the idea that the standard account of an Arab-Muslim conquest of the Iberian penninsula is absurd, as Islam has not fully formed nor were the advancing North African tribes arabicized yet. The quid of his argument is explained &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ivoox.com/falso-mito-conquista-arabe-con-audios-mp3_rf_20724520_1.html&quot;&gt;in this interview&lt;/a&gt;. As a thought experiment, I find González Ferrín’s single handed revisionism quite amusing: it might be right, but for the wrong reasons. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>

                <pubDate>Mon, 30 May 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/Mediterraneo</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Mediterraneo</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> Vislumbres de Bachofen </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;En ocasiones, el porvenir de la ciencia y, con ello, del mundo, se juega en el abismo que separa dos temperamentos. En este caso, el frío racionalismo de Mommsen, encumbrado en Berlin y la Academia Prusiana de las Ciencias, saldría airoso. Pero en la vida de las ideas, las genealogías truncas no equivalen a la muerte: la progenie electiva de Bachofen aún recorre Europa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/bachofen-mommsen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Gossman, &amp;quot;Orpheus Philologus&amp;quot;, p. 21&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>

                <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/Bachofen</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Bachofen</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> Reclaiming the good life from the Segundos Pisos </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://robbbeck.files.wordpress.com/2011/05/illich.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ivan Illich&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this winter break has been packed with activities, and a dissertation chapter is due in January, these following weeks I plan to spend as much as possible re-reading one of the intellectual (dare I say: spiritual) heroes of my youth: Ivan Illich. In the past year, I encountered Illich once again while reading about the Medieval encyclopedic tradition and Hugh of Saint Victor’s &lt;em&gt;Didascalicon&lt;/em&gt;, the 12th-century treatise on reading to which Illich dedicated a detailed commentary. A few months ago I read the engaging &lt;em&gt;Rivers North of the Future&lt;/em&gt;, a series of interviews in which Illich spelled out the theological underpinnings of his criticism of modern society.  I also came across a little book, &lt;em&gt;The Prophet from Cuernavaca&lt;/em&gt;, the first reconstruction of Illich’s activities at the CIDOC. However, it’s been my recent experiences in Mexico City that have sparked my interest in Illich’s thought once again. Mexico City in many ways stands as an example of the utter failure of the political intervention that Illich thought was still feasible in the 1970s, and through which the “Developing” world could have been spared from the ills of Capitalist modernization. While his reading of the situation, I believe, was correct, he failed to identify or address the possible agents of such an intervenetion, and he squandered his energies chastizising and re-educating American missionaries while entirely neglecting local policy-makers or institutions such as the CEPAL. At any rate, Mexico City and its sprawling net of  &lt;em&gt;segundos pisos&lt;/em&gt; feels precisely as the kind urban distopia that Illich sought to prevent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A growing number of recent publications have set out to reassess Illich’s legacy, but my aim is to dive directly into his ouevre through the wonderful FCE’s &lt;em&gt;Obras Completas&lt;/em&gt;, edited by Javier Sicilia.  I plan to re-read works that had a lasting impact in my coming of age, such as &lt;em&gt;Tools for Conviventiality&lt;/em&gt;, but also books I didn’t read back then and that now seem all the more urgent: &lt;em&gt;The Right to Useful Unemployment&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Disabling Professions&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Energy and Equity&lt;/em&gt;.  Finally, I will try to breath new life into these books by reading them side by side to Christopher Alexander’s &lt;em&gt;The Nature of Order&lt;/em&gt;, a work that I’ve been meaning to read for a while after spending several months musing over his beautiful &lt;em&gt;Pattern language&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>

                <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/think.stack/vernacular</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/think.stack/vernacular</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> El saber y el goce </title>

                <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/mondo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Mundus Symbolicus&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todo proyecto intelectual que se precie debe colocarse bajo la advocación de un mote o empresa. Uno de los primeros eventos organizados tras la fundación de la &lt;em&gt;Accademia degli Umoristi&lt;/em&gt;, en Roma, fue la serie de conferencias dictadas por el erudito friulano Girolamo Aleandro sobre el mote lucreciano de la Accademia: REDDIT AGMINE DULCI (“todo lo vuelve dulce”). A lo largo de tres jornadas, Aleandro fue desmadejando el sentido y las implicaciones del mote, cuya &lt;em&gt;pictura&lt;/em&gt; consistía en una nube, que&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[C]he formata dalle amare essalationi del mare, e sollevata in alto per virtù de raggi del Sole, si vede poco dopo in minuta, e spessa, ma gratiosa pioggia, risolta, all’in giù stillare, co ‘l motto, tolto da Lucretio nel Lib. 6: REDDIT AGMINE DULCI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La frase proviene del VI libro de &lt;em&gt;De Rerum Natura&lt;/em&gt; (631):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Postremo quoniam raro cum corpore tellus&lt;br /&gt;
est et coniunctast oras maris undique cingens,&lt;br /&gt;
debet, ut in mare de terris venit umor aquai,&lt;br /&gt;
in terras itidem manare ex aequore salso;&lt;br /&gt;
percolatur enim virus retroque remanat&lt;br /&gt;
materies umoris et ad caput amnibus omnis&lt;br /&gt;
confluit, inde super terras redit agmine dulci&lt;br /&gt;
qua via secta semel liquido pede detulit undas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O en la versión de Francisco Socas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Y por último, como la tierra está ahí con su cuerpo poroso, junto a la que hay costa marina por doquier ciñéndola, debe, tal como hasta el mar desde las tierras llega flujo de agua, manar lo mismo hasta las tierras desde la salada llanura; se va colocando pues el salitre y atrás rebota la materia líquida, y toda junta corre a la cabecera de los ríos, desde la que en dulce desfile vuelve sobre las tierras por donde el camino que por una vez abrió conduce el claro paso del agua.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-rerum&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-rerum&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En su &lt;em&gt;Mundus Symbolicus&lt;/em&gt;, compendio enciclopédico de empresas, el teórico milanés Filippo Picinelli, abrevando sin duda en el tratado manuscrito que el propio Aleandro preparó tras su conferencia, describe así el mote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;HACER BIEN A LOS ENEMIGOS. 
El ánimo generoso acostumbra pagar con beneficios las injusticias cometidas contra él. Los académicos Humoristas pintaron como su emblema general a una nube sobre el mar, la cual derrama lluvia dulce, aunque ella esté llena de vapor amargo y le pusieron el lema de Lucrecio: REDDIT AGMINE DULCIS (todo lo vuelve dulce). Filón Carpatio dice “Es propio de los cristianos hacer el bien y soportar los males”. Y Hugo Cardenal: “Como la nube convierte en dulces las aguas del mar, así el recuerdo de la pasión de Cristo, que soportó en su cuerpo, convierte en dulzura todos los sufrimientos y amarguras que los fieles padecen por él.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:fn-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:fn-1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fiel a su raíz carnavalesca—la Accademia surgió de un grupo de “belli humori” congregados para organizar las festividades del casamiento de Paolo Mancini—la Accademia se presenta como el espacio de la transmutación de los humores; espacio en que los sinsabores y desavenencias mundanas pueden volverse dulces por virtud del ejercicio de la erudición y la curiosidad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No lejos de este espíritu, Athanasius Kircher colocó su propio proyecto intelectual bajo la advocación de un mote en el que el goce sosegado de la erudición da paso a una resolución rayana en la &lt;em&gt;hybris&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/ars.png&quot; alt=&quot;Frontispicio del *Ars Magna Sciendis, Sive Combinatoria*&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En el frontispicio de su propia “Gran Arte”, que buscaba rivalizar con el &lt;em&gt;Ars&lt;/em&gt; lulliana, Kircher introdujo un mote griego tomado del &lt;em&gt;Cratilo&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Medèn kàllion è pànta eidènai&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No hay nada más hermoso que el conocimiento de todas las cosas: un mote que sor Juana Inés de la Cruz bien podría añadido en epígrafe al &lt;em&gt;Primero sueño&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;adenda-nov-2017&quot;&gt;Adenda, Nov. 2017&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nada más apropiado que, en el prefacio de &lt;em&gt;Esferas I&lt;/em&gt;, Peter Sloterdijk coloque los 3 volúmenes que conforman su épica filosófica bajo la advocación de un mote conocido y uno secreto. El primero es la conocida fórmula que de acuerdo a los comentaristas antiguos presidía el umbral de la Academia, frente al templo de las musas: “Que no entre el que no sepa geometría” (&lt;em&gt;ageometros me eisito&lt;/em&gt;). De acuerdo a Diógenes Laercio (IV, 10), fue por esta razón que Platón negó el acceso a la academia a Jenócrates. La filosofía está vedada a los ageómetras. Pero frente a esta advertencia, Sloterdijk sugiere que la geometría no es tanto una técnica o un saber como un disposición a la rememoración:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“¿Qué es un geómetra? Una inteligencia que viene del mundo de los muertos y trae consigo vagos recuerdos de su estancia en una esfera perfecta.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-rerum&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;De la naturaleza de las cosas&lt;/em&gt;, Ed. y trad. de Francisco Socas, Gredos 2003, p. 421. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-rerum&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:fn-1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;El mundo simbólico&lt;/em&gt;, Ed. y trad. del Colegio de Michoacán, p. 121-2. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:fn-1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>

                <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/think.stack/motto</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/think.stack/motto</guid>

            </item>

        
        
        

            <item>

                <title> Extraordinary Commonplaces, Robert Darnton </title>

                <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Time was when readers kept commonplace books. Whenever they came across a pithy passage, they copied it into a notebook under an appropriate heading, adding observations made in the course of daily life. Erasmus instructed them how to do it; and if they did not have access to his popular &lt;em&gt;De Copia&lt;/em&gt;, they consulted printed models or the local schoolmaster. The practice spread everywhere in early modern England, among ordinary readers as well as famous writers like Francis Bacon, Ben Jonson, John Milton, and John Locke. It involved a special way of taking in the printed word. Unlike modern readers, who follow the flow of a narrative from beginning to end, early modern Englishmen read in fits and starts and jumped from book to book. They broke texts into fragments and assembled them into new patterns by transcribing them in different sections of their notebooks. Then they reread the copies and rearranged the patterns while adding more excerpts. Reading and writing were therefore inseparable activities. They belonged to a continuous effort to make sense of things, for the world was full of signs: you could read your way through it; and by keeping an account of your readings, you made a book of your own, one stamped with your personality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See Darnton’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nybooks.com/articles/archives/2000/dec/21/extraordinary-commonplaces/&quot;&gt;original article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>

                <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>

                <link>http://localhost:4000/think.stack/commonplace</link>

                <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/think.stack/commonplace</guid>

            </item>

        
        

    </channel></rss>
